context yeah well let's do it in the
example order the game so the
perceptions of the forest that you can
use to establish your minds you're not
bothered by anything in the village it's
not the actual perceiving of the forest
that I'm perceiving them in the forest
I'm in the forest which is usually how
people practice their meditation it's
quite the opposite
you have perception of the forest when
you're not in the forest that's how it's
done rightly which means it's not actual
perceiving on the level of your nose
smell taste and touch and so it's on the
level of the mind mind perceives the
mood of the forest the context of the
forest from when you were in the forest
so if your mind is established upon the
context which literally means
circumstances an environment that
provides a basis for more particular
action so now despite the urine in the
village your mind refuses to abandon the
context of the greater forest which
means then your time in the village it's
only going to be minimal for whatever
necessary reason but it won't be
uprooting the general context of the
perception of the forest
I am the forest dweller I live in the
forest I am the forest and that's all
Buddha said if you develop perception of
the forest if you develop context of the
forest no particular actions done in the
town or whatever else will they be able
to affect you know but you know totally
not no particular sight sound smell
taste touches from the town of the
village will be able to affect you
because the mind still perceives itself
on the basis of the context of the
forest but if you get careless you
forget that you can start giving into
particular sight sound smell taste
touches in the village you drop off from
the context of the forest exactly
so once you you are established upon the
greater context the context of the
forest all you need to do is guard your
senses on a particular basis as in just
don't intend
go with the unwholesome and context of
the forest will be maintained and then
the woman goes further and says well
what's even greater context in the
context of the forest because if
something happens to the forest which is
your context of your mind then you would
be affected but then you go for you you
look at you look at the higher because
context of the forest is greater or the
context of any particular village of the
town but if you look higher you can find
the context of the earth planet Earth
element of Earth call it whatever you
want whether you're in the forest
whether you're in the town
whether you're elsewhere you are on
earth so that's even greater context but
as I said if you truly start developing
context of the earth that would require
some serious letting go and giving up of
basically your life and your own body in
other words if you're still like
concerned over things in your
environment over your Kuti your dwelling
this woodland with Everland means you're
not giving things up so how can you then
transcend the greater context when you
still refuse to let go of the particular
context so if you develop a mind upon
the context of Earth it would result in
you not even regarding your own body as
belonging to you anymore that truly
means developing the greater context the
greater perception and that's what we
encourage it to contemplate the four
elements a song because he will result
in this passion towards this particular
manifestation of material form on the
basis of the greater context of Earth
because yeah whatever whatever you look
in this body it's it's the elements that
compose everything else in the world
which means all of that is inferior to
the great basis of the context of Earth
that provides these elements so I'm
saying is it because sometimes people
can think that simply by thinking about
a greater if they are developing the
context but you will know you're
developing the context when concern for
your own life and body sense is failing
anything that happen to you sickness
disappears you're not concerned because
your mind is established upon that
create the context
so in that sense yeah that's what I want
to say you can see the context
determines the extent of your perception
so to the extent of the perception of
the earth that context defines
everything particular that comes your
way and whether you're going to be
affected by it or not and the literal
translation well the literal Bollywood that can be
well the literal Bollywood that can be
translated as extent most literally is
casinos and that's exactly why the earth
Casino the water fire air casino and it
would encourage these practices so you
it's not cussing usually people think
escena practice is staring at the clay
pots and red colors and whatnot
no it's developing these perception of
the context that will have to result in
this passion and abandoning of anything
inferior to it and that's exactly what
woody would say he said demand the
target understood the extent of the
earth he understood gratification in earth
he understood gratification in earth
danger in Earth and escape in earth and
what is then to be said about everything
else it's inferior to earth but then he
went further earth water fire air the
four colors the infinite space and
consciousness and he said the
consciousness is like that the most
refined of them all as in the context of
simple presence whether it's their
suffering that's present happiness
perception of villager all of it but it
all has in common is its present it has
a reason and you can discern that extent
but by that time you virtually gonna be
full on other hunt developing basically
cessation of perception and feeling but
you don't have to it's enough to do the
extent of Earth so it's not like
progression you have to go through all
ten extends all tanka seen as Hotel ten
context no just start with the lowest
one it will be enough for final
liberation because in order to properly
develop the context of the earth that
you are partaking in with your own
experience right here right now you
you will abandon everything in failure
to it any sense of ownership in regard
to this particular insignificant little
body any like body of others presences
of others houses homes villages anything
anything it's inferior to the to the to
the planet earth to the element of Earth
the planet Earth is made of the element
of Earth that gives context to the
planet Earth that gives context to the
island your own Mountain your own forest
durian could you sitting in your own
body that you're possessing and you
could see all these great mountains are
already greater than your body
they're gonna be here longer than you
will they've been here longer than you
you ever will be yet it's still not
seeing that context not allowing it to
do not knowing how to maintain it the
background of your mind you get pulled
with the particular senses and then you
sort of pervert the whole picture and
then you are the center you are the
context that's why the five modes of
being for unenlightened mind are the
five contexts which is the five
hindrances the context of sensuality
context of ill-will restlessness doubt
and those are all contexts those are all
general context they determine your
particular actions would you be able to
engage with sensuality we like with
sensual act pursuits if the context of
sexuality is not pushing you that way if
you haven't given into the pressure of
the context of sensuality would you be
then deciding the particular acts of all
sexuality no but then at the same time
if you were not doing the particular
acts of sensuality would that context be
maintained no because it needs
maintenance you need to be engaging in
sensuality to be maintained sensuality
that's where sense restraint has to come
first you stop maintaining it so that
you can discern it now the wholesome
context the context it's on the level of
nature of things it will be good
bye-bye the extent of the earth water
fire or these general perceptions that
you can use the abandoning failure ones
and they pertain to the nature of things
that they don't require you're doing see
presence of your body already means
presence of the element of Earth but
which which side of that presence you're
gonna you're gonna think about you're
gonna establish yourself you're gonna be
concerned with the general side of it
which is element of Earth is present
that cannot be mined because how can I
own the element of Earth or the
particular manifestation of the element
of Earth is this body of mine in which
case you will be appropriating it and is
regarding it is yours so if you start
that's what the Buddha was saying to to
rahula like be like earth be like water
not in some phytic sense no because you
can the perception of your own body here
contains the greater perception of Earth
and the perception of your own body here
it's inferior to the greater perception
of Earth in regarded as in the
perception of your own body here is on
the basis of the context of element of
Earth element of solidity cohesion
fluidity the four Great elements and the
four great characteristics that this
particular body has but it's other way
around these are not characteristics of
your body your body is the product of
these characteristics and you realize
you can own this you can own cohesion
you can own solidity you can own heat
just like a vigorous element of heat
well it's ambiguous only because you
still give priority to the particular
result of that context which is this
body of mine and these senses that I can
use so if you own abandoned hindrances
you develop greater context
you wanna ban the hindrance of sloth and
torpor replace it with a context of
something active walking back and forth
would you be able to move your feet left
right left right left right if there is
no general intention to walk back and
forth which endures and persists while
you keep moving your feet left and right
you're going to stop after you move your
left foot well if you're going back and
forth yeah oh I'm thinking about behind
while I'm going forth because otherwise
I don't know what I'm doing
no you have the context of walking back
and forth as one intentional think
that's what defines all these particular
acts you do and that's why I kept what
it carries the context your particular
acts that are defined by the context
maintain the context that's what you
don't have to keep thinking I'm walking
I'm walking I'm walking all you need to
do is not forget that you already know
that you are walking you can't be
outside of the context you can only
replace the unwholesome context with
awesome context you can only replace the
unwholesome perception of continuity
with wholesome perceptual continuity
because the context indoors while you're
performing actions on account of it so
replace the context of sensuality with
context of restrained context available
with context of loving-kindness context
of doubt the context of comprehension
context of sloth and torpor with the
context of wakefulness cuz it's
effortless you doing that's not
effortless but if you started sending
the context rightly that's effortless
because walking maintains the context of
of walking but context of walking gives
the context to the actual particular
movements of your feet and the whole act
there's nothing for you there to do
you're just walking because the context
of the walking is present all you need
to do is start descending the context of
the walking then you'll never have a
problem doing walking meditation or
being lazy but imagine all you need to
do is attend to the design of activity
so to speak
well yes because it is a form of
perception but the problem is if you sit
the perception of walking back and forth
usually just plays into people's
missmiss misconceived notion of
meditation of on perceiving my left foot
my right foot my left foot my right foot
after perception of walking perception
of walking as in I have to keep telling
myself and perceiving that I'm walking
in order to know that I'm walking but
you already know that you're walking
otherwise you wouldn't be able to walk
in the first place
so that's that knowledge is that context
that's why mindfulness of the context
brings comprehension brings the sermon
bring Samadhi brings composure of that
context context is composed if it's the
right context and that you can see how
it's all basically just completely tied
in together whether it's mindfulness
context casinos Samadhi or discs it all
leads to the same thing clarity of
mindfulness and discernment of the
nature of things because if you're
walking is determined by the context of
the walking in context of the walking is
carried through the walking where is the
room for the sense of self who is saying
I am walking there isn't any room it's
almost like an automated action but in
only only way to understand how
automated it is is to abandon your sense
of self through developing this creative
context through discerning it in other
words you're either for to Gina who you
neither are you stomach hurt or die
aren't you you can't have a clear sort
of step outside from either and and then
decide you're either immersed into not
seeing the context or you start seeing
the context yeah sure the context of the
nature what is nature of things its
context of those things so the Dhamma is
the universal context and what's most
universal about anything good bad far
near personal and personal it's that it
has a resonance
they cannot provide that lasting
satisfaction of ownership and because of
that cannot be owned so it's a niche is
that universal context one of them
unsatisfactoriness is another universal
context the result of these universal
context context s is that your
experience is experienced or distant
cannot belong to me because it's it's
determined by this greater context which
I'm not saying as I said how can you own
a notion of cohesion
how can you own solidity fluidity but
see you see this fluidity solidity
cohesion you see that secondary to the
sense of self because you haven't
developed the right context in regard to
send yourself on account of which you
would have discerned these things those
are the four Great elements the four
great context oh yeah you could approach
it through the through the contemplation
comprehension discernment or funny
change right well yeah that's that's on
the level of inferior perception so
you're not seeing the context there and
that doesn't work in the same sense what
I said that perception of the forest
doesn't work if you think that
perception of the forest is perceiving
the forest and perceiving the forest
embassy in the forest because if
perception of the change is what the
nature is then you will have to die in
order to give up your life as another
hunt would give up his life through
understanding give up attachment to the
life so how can you perceive how can you
give up death if the only way to give up
that is perceiving you dying means you
have to basically be dead to become
another hunter which that means doesn't
matter what you do to run your life
because death will make another hunt but
that's not what a Buddhist said on the
contrary it's the presence of the thing
because of that presence you get to
discern on each
so Nietzsche is not a perception of
change that's all secondary to it and
each is basically perception of I cannot
own this even if I want to it's a
perception of this is against me it's a
perception of independent of me yet I
depend on it it's basically putting that
which you've been putting second as
first and putting that which you've been
putting as first I my sense of self as
second and if sense of self is second
then it's on myself anymore because if
in order for it to be maintained itself
needs to be primary needs to be the
center of my experience needs to be -
needs to be master needs to be in
control
exactly context is not like this it's
not a it's not an objective thing you
need to know what to look for in order
to discern that we have like infinite
amount of contexts because they're
determined by what you're looking for
that's an instruction of another the
right instruction of somebody they stood
up and no higher of the ideally the
Buddha himself is required because you
will not be discerning this context cuz
if you manage to discern this context on
your own context of a nature you become
some assembler
so the most universal context is the
context that the Dharma is laid laid
upon the lamas total so you need to know
what to look for you need to know what
signs and tokens to start discerning to
develop the perception of the greater
context and yeah the most great context
is I can't own anything even if I want
to and that context becomes your mode of
being - the clarity of comprehension you
developed in regard to it nothing
particularly will we'll be able to sway
you or or perturb you or disturb you
because you don't own already this own
body of yours let alone anything that
can come through these senses it all
becomes even more and that's
exactly what how the Buddhist said that
if you develop money regard to the
extent the Cocina you would abandon
things because you'd abandon the things
in regard to the great perception of the
like casino birth and then he said what
is to be said about everything inferior
to it
well that that cannot even be like this
cannot bother me anymore let alone
anything inferior to it see if you truly
understood the most fundamental context
of a Nietzsche in regarding everything
that has a nature to manifest that's
basically sorted party that's that's
what it means whatever has the context
of arising because of that has the
context of cessation has the context of
non ownership non appropriation
indifference dispassion all these other
contexts come from that context how can
discern a context if you don't even
start having an idea of the context no
instruction no reflection no question no
interrogation no looking for the meaning
of the context when all you do is look
at the particular thing that's in front
of you side side sound sound smell smell
taste taste touch time sitting sitting
walking left-right back-forth left-right
like basically it's a it's a well I'm
sure many people are not aware it but in
practice it becomes like like a cop-out
you try to overcome the context of
suffering context of non enlightenment
through denying that there is a context
at all to focusing and staring as hard
as you can it was right in front of you
so when there is in front you don't
think about back in speculating about
being in the present moment that's
usually what people mean by it spoke was
focused to the one point wherever you
forget everything else and that kind of
temporary oblivion in regard to the
context feels like freedom off the
context but that's not a lasting freedom
and if there is not a lasting freedom
how can you say it's free how can you
say I'm free when somebody else
something else did take dictates my time
of freedom means you're not free
you just get a little bit of break from
your imprisonment the only true way of
freedom is to understand what did you
wanna say the nature of things how do
you understand the nature things by
understanding what's most Universal in
them what's most Universal in anything
that manifests
well that's universal thing he has
manifested on its own because of that
it's impermanent because of that cannot
provide my pleasure pleasure for me and
that's the Dhamma because if you were to
understand the Dhamma the meaning of the
Dhamma just by looking just by listening just
just by looking just by listening just
by touching just by sitting moving
touching whatever else
well the Buddha would have said so
you'll be talking about all these ways
of establishing and discerning the
nature of things and not resting until
there's like until you're sure in your
knowledge and then notice the knowledge
the knowledge that you know as well so
you could see that practically when
people and the practicing the focusing
meditation to one point it's all done
from the context or trying to deny even
or get rid of the creative context
because greater context is unpleasant
that's what a person who invested a lot
of the time in energy in years in this
kind of concentration practice because
very uneasy if that concentration
practice is compromised or questioned or
even just challenged by somebody not
even at them just they might read
something with somebody said and
dismisses it and they will be affected
existentially they would feel need to
defend it
what because they become aware
unwillingly of the greater context and
what is the most fundamental nature of
the greater context any context for that
matter its manifested it's there cannot
be on cannot provide lasting
satisfaction so you realized ended there
ironically for many people practice of
Dharma through that concentration
meditation object and technique takes
them away from the
because Dhamma is knowing the context
not running away from it and covering it
up and that's the danger of the wrong
view you can think you can be thinking
you're doing the Dhamma rightly well in
reality you're just developing your own
views further and further and further
but it's easy to uproot but obviously
the longer you don't do it the more
courage to do it you're gonna need and
the point will come when theoretically
the carriage will be possible but
practically becomes impossible and you
will do it just if you ever come across
yourself okay if I were to drop all my
knowledge all my techniques everything
we do man wouldn't be able to suffer
would I be affected by suffering in the
first place sure my neighbor perform a
meditation technique in perfect
management and my teacher always tells
me what I need to hear it's all great
and I've been celebrating practicing
this for 45 50 years that's so fun now
put all that aside if suffering with the
rise of any kind shape or form for
whatever reason would you be affected
first and then it would you have to do
all of these things even if you just
need to do them for a second still would
your doing be responds to being
effective or suffering in the first
place did you practice make you completely
did you practice make you completely
completely impotent in regards to any
form of suffering as in you are not
touched by it in the first place if the
answer is yes correct carry on the
answer is no there you go that's your
work there doesn't mean and everything
that has been done with complete waste
but you'll find that out only afterwards
once you fear self from suffering then
you'll see what you've been doing was
wasteful and what wasn't
so the only method of discerning complex
is learning what the context is and
they're making an effort to discern